Well, Anthropic just launched routines,
which allows Claude to kick off
automations via schedule, trigger, or
even web hook. And this closes the loop
and basically turns Claude into a
dedicated automation platform competing
with no code drag and drop builders like
NADEN and others. In this video, I'm
going to show you guys how you can build
routines very quickly. I'm going to give
you guys a couple of demos and I'm going
to walk you through step by step setting
up your own routines on both the Claude
desktop interface as well as behind the
scenes via API. Okay, so for the most
prototypical example, I have a daily
mailbox summary plus draft routine. And
what I'm doing here is I just clicked
run now because they have a little demo
or test feature that allows you to
actually run it and then see the inputs
and outputs live. If I click on this
little runs button, you'll see that all
I've really done is I've just fed in a
prompt. And this is the exact same thing
as cloud code. It's just occurring on a
standardized cloud container, not on my
computer. And in this case, I'm just
testing it using their interface, but
you can also schedule it. You can have
it trigger based off web hook. And then
you can also send an API request to
trigger it. And so you can trigger it
based on incoming data. You can trigger
it based off outgoing data. It's very
powerful. If anybody has watched my
previous video on Agentic Workflows,
this is basically the standardized and
enterprise version of Agentic Workflows.
So this is now searching through Gmail
emails. It's actually doing everything
more or less that I would normally do if
running this locally on my computer. The
only difference being obviously that
because it's occurring on the cloud,
it's not something that I realistically
am going to want to have to steer.
Typically, you want to be a lot clear
about the instructions and make sure
that it has all the information that it
needs. After that, it's just going to go
through various tool calls and
everything like that until it gets to
the definition of done, which in my case
is going to be, hey, once you're
finished, use a Slack connector to send
me an update. Now, on the Cloud Code
docs page, the majority of the use cases
are what I'd consider to be overly
technical things like backlog
maintenance, alert triage, bespoke code
review. I mean, most people don't even
know what any of the stuff means. Um,
but I want you to know this is basically
a standin replacement for automation.
You can automate anything using this
tool. And what's really cool is you can
do it using natural language. So, what
I've done is I've developed a cloud
skill that you can import into your own
workspace. Then you can just give that
skill any pre-existing workflow whether
it's in natural language written as an
SOP or it's something on a no code tool
like naden or make.com. Back to the
skill page here. You can see it's found
two unreads. The thing is I don't really
care about this because if you think
about it, this is the conversation
thread. What I want to do is I want to
see this Slack update that was sent to
my DMs because you know if I'm using
this like a traditional automation,
that's where I'd probably be getting the
notification. So, if I go, I actually
see I did receive a notification at
12:01 where it pulled my own reds and
then it fed me the information as well
as like a highle summary along with a
polite decline that it drafted as well
as an acceptance for for this one. And I
can go on to my email and I can actually
open up the drafts and I could I could
see them all as well. And just because
I'm trying not to dox all of these
people too hard, um, you know, in this
case, I immediately drafted, hey Corey,
thanks for reaching out. Tell the other
Nick I own one. Happy to come on. Send
over a few time slots that work on your
end. Uh, and then I just removed the two
email, but that was previously
populated. Okay, so that's probably the
simplest example of a demo. And I just
did all this stuff uh live using the
test feature because I wanted to show
you that that's how it works. But you
can also schedule it. And then you can
also fire things off based off web hooks
and API calls. So what I'm going to do
next is I'm very quickly going to show
you how the scheduling feature works.
And then after I'm going to show you how
you can use triggers like web hooks and
so on and so forth to run your routines.
Once we're done with that, I'll actually
walk through like the UX and show you
guys uh more of the deep dive behind how
this works. So anyway, for scheduling
purposes, all I need to do is go back to
the routine that I made a moment ago. I
click on this little button here, and
then I can just select a different
trigger. So in this case, I have call
via API, but I could also click
schedule. And as you see here, we have
this little visual interface where I
could select hourly, daily, and so on
and so forth. Because this is going to
be an email triage flow, I'm probably
going to want to run this pretty early
before I wake up. I'm waking up around
5:20 these days, so it'll probably be
about 510. And what I should note is you
can add multiple of these triggers at
any point in time. So now after saving,
if I go back to routines, you'll see
there's a little calendar feature here.
And you can now see that there's a daily
mailbox summary plus draft opened at
5:10, as well as a couple of other ones
that I was playing around with earlier
today. You don't have to pay attention
to those. What that means is without me
having to do anything, the exact same
exercise is going to occur. The agent is
going to check my mailbox using the
Gmail connector. It's going to run
through whatever SOP or logic that I
gave it, which in this case was just,
hey, go see if we've had any previous
email communicate. And then it's going
to draft up the message and send it to
me in Slack. Okay. What I have here is
another routine. This one takes a
transcript that is generated using
Fireflies, which is a transcript service
that joins your call, listens to what
you say, and then basically stores it
all as text. And essentially what I'm
going to do just for the purposes of
this demo is I'm going to do it via API
request, but I'm going to show you guys
as well how you can hook it up via web
hook so it just fires automatically. So
I have my transcript to proposal routine
right over here. And I could click run
now, but there's no actual transcript.
The instructions here are I give you a
transcript via API call. So what I'm
going to do is I'm going to open up a
cloud code instance. I'm just going to
have it send an API request using uh
this transcript.
And then I'm just going to press enter.
And I'm not going to expand this because
I've just hard-coded an API key for uh
demo purposes. But you can see here what
it's going to start off by doing is
basically sending that curl request as a
text payload and then also generating
the proposal entirely on its own. And
when this occurs, it's actually going to
trigger that routine. I guess I already
just leaked my API key. Whatever the
hell. Um it's going to fire that
routine, which it's done right over
here. And now it's actually running in
the cloud with the full transcript and
whatever the deal terms are of the, you
know, conversation. And so I can
actually open this up and then I can see
what's going on. So you can see I give
you a transcript via API call. I want
you to create a full proposal using one
of my other AI agents in a managed
session. And this is where managed
sessions come in handy, which if you
guys didn't know is just a similar way
that you could set up different
endpoints out there that allow AI to
basically create an an interconnected
network of managed agents or agents that
all have their own siloed containers
both for security and then safety
purposes. So, it's just verifying that
we actually have what we need for Slack.
And now it's going to go ahead and
generate a high-quality proposal. Now, I
just want to be clear about what problem
exactly this solves. The old way of
designing automations typically involved
some sort of event or outside trigger
like a schedule, maybe something that
occurred, you know, at 5:00 a.m. every
morning or whatever. That event would be
fed into a platform like NAN, which was
responsible for basically proceeding
through a chain of logic that you
created. You know, it' be a bunch of
drag and drop uh nodes that you put
together to do some function. In this
case, this is a Reddit scraper for a
live build that I did for one of my
communities. And see this whole section
in the middle here, this logic, this can
take a fair amount of time to put
together. You know, you have to drag and
drop all these nodes, you have to set up
all of these credentials, you have to do
all the authentication, you got to get
the data and and map the right variables
and the fields. This is really like
where the meat and potatoes of your work
as somebody that was looking to automate
your business um um came in. Okay? And
then from there, your NAD system,
typically, it doesn't just like work by
itself. It does something to some
platform, right? So it'll then grab its
output and then shove that into Slack or
maybe some sort of CRM somewhere or
whatever it is that you do, some
database. The new way is basically the
exact same thing. You have an event,
okay? And that event is either an API
call. It's a web hook or it's some sort
of schedule. So again, you know, waking
it up at 5:00 a.m. every morning. It's
just instead of putting that into NADN
and then having to build all that stuff
yourself with those drag and drop nodes,
all you have to do, okay, is just give
it some natural language which is far
easier obviously with some very high
level instructions and then it can then
output things as uh ND did before to you
know some other platform Slack or CRM
and so the reason why I'm equating it
like this is because routines
effectively solve that middle problem.
Uh I've made some videos in the past to
the tune of N8N is over because XYZ
thing is now launched and it does it way
better and you know sometimes a specific
feature was missing that you know N8N or
some other no code platform handled. Um
that didn't make it an exactly one to
one overlap but routines are uh cla's
literal 1 to1 overlap. It replaces the
exact same functionality. It's capable
of scheduling. It's capable of
orchestrating workflows and so on and so
forth. And it really is like the next
step in agentic uh execution of
knowledge tasks. When all this stuff
finishes, I actually have the proposal
right over here. I can take a look at
that. Click this button to open it in a
new page. And you can see I now have the
proposal, which is just part of the
template of the manage agent that
generates this thing. Pull out all of
the data. So, you know, we're an AI
content writing marketplace that matches
business clients with vetted freelancer
writers. And then this is leftclick,
which you know is pitching them. And so,
these are the sorts of proposals that we
actually send day-to-day. And hopefully
you guys see how easy it is to actually
like integrate a routine or some sort of
API eventbased system into your
infrastructure in like two minutes. Uh
boy, have we come a long way from back
in the day when me designing that
proposal generator would have taken like
2 and 1 half to 3 hours. The current UX
for routines looks like this. And in
order to get there, all you have to do
is type in cloud.ai/code/
routines. You'll be given a page that
looks something like this where you can
see all routines stored in a grid-like
pattern over here alongside their title,
the time that they are running, and then
also the the next scheduled run as well
as what looks like some category listing
which they provide uh with or without
you. There's also a calendar view and so
you can see the actual ones that are
going to be executed and exactly which
times they're going to be executed. And
so here I created a couple of demos,
daily nicks, arrive mention scan,
morning inbox drafts and news video
ideas. You can see that today this one's
going to execute at 651, this one at
7:43, and this one at 8:17. So, you also
get a little bit of a visual aspect
there. When you click new routine up in
the top right, it'll immediately ask you
for some information like the name. So,
I'm just going to provide a quick demo
here called mailbox drafter. Next, you
can describe what Claude should do in
each session. So, this is where you
basically give it a prompt. And this
prompt is essentially analogous to a
skill. Just like in a skill, you have a
standardized list of steps that you need
the model to take in order to perform
some economically valuable piece of work
for you. Um, so too should you construct
this routine description like a list of
SOPs or steps to allow it to perform uh
a tasks for you. It's just my
recommendation here is be a little bit
more precise than you are probably in
your skill because whereas in your skill
you could modify things on the fly,
change your trajectory of the task and
so on and so forth, here the routine
occurs entirely hands-off, meaning that
it basically needs to work almost
perfectly every time. So decrease the
total scope of possible messups and
screw-ups that it could make by being as
clear and precise as possible. But for
instance, I wrote pull all of my unreads
using the provided Gmail connector. More
on that in a sec. For each unread, check
if there's any pre-existing
conversations with that contact. If so,
pull those two for context. Then draft
replies based on what you know about me
and the context of the task. Once done,
use the Slack connector. More on that in
a second to send me an update. And so,
as you can see here, um, you know, you
can make this about as long or as as
short as you want. I don't believe
there's a length limit. I went and I
checked just by pasting this a bunch of
times and I couldn't find anything. So,
I would definitely lean on the side of
more contacts as opposed to less. From
there, you can select a repository. So,
whatever repository you want. I'm just
going to say this business one. You can
select a model type. So, I'm going to
use Opus 4.61 mil. And then you can also
select which cloud environment you want
to run it in. And so, you can hear
basically create a cloud environment
with a bunch of environment variables,
keys, uh, you know, API credentials and
so on and so forth as needed. So, in my
case, I'm fine with default. I'm just
going to move on. You can then select a
trigger. So, you can schedule it. You
can go via GitHub event or you can go
via API. Now, realistically, this is
probably something you're going to want
to do on a schedule since we are just
going to be going through our on reds
and then drafting. But for demonstration
purposes, I'm just going to go via API.
And the whole idea is by doing this,
I'll be able to very quickly call and
then test in another Cloud Code instance
to show you guys what's happening live.
So, I'm just going to add a trigger. And
then once we've added said trigger,
we're going to receive a little curl
request, which is a snippet of code that
you can give any model. And finally, now
we just need to add our connector. So,
here I'm going to click add connector.
And then I'm going to connect my own
Gmail. By the way, if you don't have a
connector, just head on down to Claude
code settings, then go to connectors
over here. Then you can actually add uh
just clicking on this little connect
button. When you do, it'll ask to
connect Claude to your Gmail account.
You can click continue and then you can
sign into the particular one that you
want. So, in my case, this I'm also
going to need one other connector if you
guys think about it because I'm going to
want a Slack message sent. So, here I
can use this little search bar and then
click a plus button. Then I'll just have
to perform again some OOTH in a new
browser tab. Here I'm going to click
allow. And just like any simple OOTH
screen, we're now going to be connected.
So now what we can do is we can go back
to the routine and then I can add the
connector manually. From here, you'll be
given a token. You can copy that token,
store it somewhere safe. So that's what
I'm going to do here. And now we
basically have our skill or our routine
ready to go. Okay. And then once you're
done, just head over to the run now in
the top right hand corner to basically
start the workflow run. And uh we're
just going to do this here using the GUI
graphical user interface for testing
purposes. But you'll see a new little
run just populated. So I'm going to go
down here and you'll see all we're
really doing is we're just sending it
this message. Once it's done, it'll use
the Slack connector to send me an
update. You can see it's already
starting to fire off a tool search. So
I'll just double back when it's done.
And I should note, I mean, I'm watching
it here, but the whole idea is that I
don't even know that this thing's going
on, right? This was triggered uh ideally
on a schedule or something like that,
and I just wake up in the morning to my
Slack uh message with a bunch of
different emails and their various
drafts. If I head back over here, you
can see that we actually have both of
those fed in. Um, looks like somebody
invited me for a podcast interview and
then somebody else asked me a couple of
questions about a few things here.
Finally, I want to show you guys how
easy it is to convert workflows that you
built on third party tools like NAD, for
instance, into routines. And what's
really cool about NAND is they allow you
just to like mouse over if you hold
shift and then hold command C or just
right click and press copy. And then now
you basically have access to a bunch of
JSON. And you could tell just by me
pasting it in. This is like JSON or the
syntax that these nodes are represented
in if we're talking through text. Well,
anyway, if I go back to anti-gravity,
which contains my little cloud code
window, and then I type in this JSON,
and then at the very top, I say use the
routine generator to turn this naden
workflow into a routine. Okay, I'm just
going to divide this to make it really
simple. Uh what this is going to do is
use the skill that I'm giving all of you
guys out of the box to basically turn
this into a flow that we can call just
using natural language. So I'm not
necessarily going to encourage you to
use all of your workflows or to port
them over from NADN or some other no
code tool to uh claude's back end.
Reason being is you know when you're
dealing in the domain of tokens things
are going to be a little bit more
expensive than dealing entirely in the
domain of compute. And really the point
is not hey just turn all your nadn or
make.com workflows into routines. The
point is more like, you know, if you
have something you can build today that
previously would have taken you a couple
of hours in NAN, might make more sense
just to oneshot it as a routine. But,
um, you know, what this will do really
quickly is just go ahead and do the
creation. So, as you guys can see here,
it's doing some thinking. It's loading
the routines. In this case, it's just
going to schedule one cuz I didn't
provide any context as to how I wanted
to run it. Um, but yeah, here we go.
It's now going to fetch stories from the
HackerN Algolia API, extract the hits,
format them into a markdown report, and
commit it, which was what the actual
flow was doing. So, just like this one
here, if I click execute workflow, this
goes through the scraper. It then
generates a bunch of hits basically from
um a website called Hacker News.
HackerNews is the source here, which in
this case is going to contain a bunch of
different um comments like this one on
how open source AI is the path forward.
Certainly not when Claude drops a
freaking update like this. Well, the
same routine is going to work here the
exact same way. And you can see it just
said routine created and fired hacker
use AI stories fetch, right? And what's
really cool about this is I mean it's
it's just so easy for me to to change
things. Um so I mean right now this is
obviously going to fetch that data,
right? And you know fetching that data
is okay, but what am I going to do with
it? It's just sort of like stuck here,
right? You know, if I were in NAD, I'd
have to modify this. Uh it'd be
significantly harder to modify this
here. I can literally just go connectors
Slack. Okay, save. I can then set it to
run on, you know, 733 MDT or via API
request, which I'm going to click done.
And now what I can also do is I can go
back here and I can say great, update
this so that it sends me a message in
Slack with the scrape after it's done.
And now in 3 seconds, you know, it can
make an HTTP request over to the routine
and just edit it on the fly for me. I
don't have to drag and drop any notes.
It's much easier and much faster. Okay,
so hopefully you guys can see that this
has a lot of potential and you're likely
to see larger and larger flows be passed
off to agents in this manner. Um, I
didn't really give you guys an
extraordinarily comprehensive look at
all the different things you could do
with this, but just off the top of my
head, some ways that I'm implementing
this in my agency today, some ways that
I've already done so, and some ways that
I can I'm going to continue to do so
after this video are I'm going to
replace all of my proposal generators
with these built-in routines. I'm going
to connect a couple of additional
routines so that after a call, like a a
sales call with a prospect, um, I'll
receive a web hook with um, essentially
like a transcript. I'm going to feed
that transcript into a routine that's
going to generate an immediate post call
email and then uh like a workflow
diagram draft based on our conversations
that I can also pin alongside it just
for the impression of of more effort and
higher perceived quality. Uh when we
send out the proposal, I'm going to be
monitoring to see if somebody's signed.
When they do, it's going to route back
to another routine via a web hook, which
is going to proceed with the next step,
which is sending them a message with an
email with an onboarding uh you know,
calendar notification, as well as
congratulating them and thanking them on
on coming aboard.
You guys can automate more or less all
of the non like human facetime steps in
a business right now. And it's not like
you couldn't before. It's just in order
to do it before it was pretty laborious
and you needed a fair amount of knowhow.
Um now as long as you understand sort of
the routine spec and more or less what
I've showed you in this video, you guys
are good to go. So it's an exciting time
to be in AI and automation. Hopefully
you guys appreciated this video. Looking
forward to the next one. Catch y'all on
it.